Inventory of the Japanese diaspora oral history project records
Hoover Institution Archives
Japanese diaspora oral history project records
2017
2017C42
Hoover Institution Archives
74 digital files (13.7 GB)
Digital interview recordings of Japanese Americans relating to immigration to the United States from Japan, internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, and the post-war Japanese American community. Interviews conducted by Kaoru Ueda. Includes images of diaries, newsletters, and other textual material.
Ueda, Kaoru.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Digital interview recordings of Japanese Americans relating to immigration to the United States from Japan, internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, and the post-war Japanese American community. Interviews conducted by Kaoru Ueda. Includes images of diaries, newsletters, and other textual material.
Japan--Emigration and immigration.; Japanese Americans.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
- Ashizawa, Philip, 2017 March 10 (Reading room workstation)
  Biographical Note
  The third generation owner of Soko hardware store, which opened in the 1920s. Obtained a copy of his father's memoir.
- Hanabusa, Kazue, 2017 May 24
  Member of the Buddhist church in Palo Alto. Born in Hilo, Hawaii, and moved to San Francisco.
- Inoue, Keith Paul, 2017 April 21
  Resident minister of Wesley Methodist Church, San Jose.
- Iwatsubo, Akemi, 2017 May 3
  Volunteer at the Buddhist church in Palo Alto.
- Kashiwagi, Hiroshi, 2017 February 24 and March 3
  Born in Loomis, CA. His father ran a fish store. His mother and children were about to return to Japan, but his father opened a store, so they remained in the U.S. No-no boy at Tule Lake camp. Published books and screen plays. Librarian at San Francisco City Library.
- Kuramoto, Shirley Toshiko, 2017 April 21
  Honoree of senior appreciation brunch at the Sakura matsuri, San Francisco, in 2017 for her contributions as an active community member: screen writer at Yu-Ai Kai, docent at Japanese American National Museum.
- Kurotaki, Koshi, 2017 March 1
  Born in Aomori, Japan, as the second son of a Soto temple. Decided to work as a Soto priest in the U.S. after his older brother succeeded the temple.
  Scope and Contents note
  Kurotaki discusses how to maintain the temple as a traditional religious place for Issei and Japanese expats and to find solutions to evolve as the Japanese American community changes.
- Matsueda, June, 2017 May 3
  Member of the Buddhist church in Palo Alto. Born in the U.S. and went to Japan on her husband's Fulbright scholarship.
- Okumura, Sakaye, 2017 June 6
  A family member of chrysanthemum grower in Redwood City.
- Thow, George, 2017 April 27
  Ministerial assistant, Buddhist Churches of America, Enmanji Buddhist Temple, Sebastopol.
- Tolosa, Joanne, 2017 March 10
  Head minister, Konko Church of San Francisco. A Chinese philippina who converted from Catholicism to Konko, which is neither shinto nor Buddhist.
  Tolosa discusses how the Konko church's open door policy and egalitarian system resonated with her, and how the Japanese service is now combined with the English service, as the members have become predominantly English speakers.
- Yamaichi, Jimi, 2017 May 19
  Curator of the Japanese American Museum, San Jose.
- Yano, Jane, 2017 May 3
- Yasuko, Fukuda, 2017 February 27 and March 10
  Kibei. Born in Sacramento to a Buddhist priest father. His mother took the children to take care of their temple at Fukui/Shiga. Returned to the U.S. in the 1950s without any English. Married a Kibei who died at 38, leaving two children.
- Yasutake, Joseph, 2017 May 16
  Board member of the Japanese American Museum, San Jose.